Michael Lee

Data Developer

Washington, DC Phone: 414-550-3410 www.mikelee.co Email: mdlee12@gmail.com

SUMMARY OF QUALIFICATIONS

A developer living in the Washington, DC area specializing in the creation of graphics, web applications, and other data-driven projects. I teach workshops on R programming and data visualization and also enjoy baking baklava, biking, and playing word games.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

RESEARCHER

American Institutes for Research (April 2019 - Present)

- Founding and lead developer of InCompass, an R/React web app analyzing International Large-Scale Assessments (ILSAs) data. Co-leads weekly meetings and directs development tasks to a team of four R programmers. Performs feature request reviews and facilitates development workflow on GitHub. Deploys and performs debugs with cloud architect.
- Developed 20+ animations products shared on the @EdNCES Twitter feed.
- Designed automated production systems for custom reporting of student and teacher level survey data for IAP study websites. Used R to manipulate and reshape survey results and D3.js to create interactive visualizations.
- Contributed to the development of <u>EdSurvey</u>, an R package used for analyzing education survey data from the National Center for Education Statistics (NCES). Led 10+ training workshops regarding R programming and EdSurvey

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE

<u>American Institutes for Research</u> (July 2015 - March 2019)

- Founding and lead developer of iNRD, an interactive shiny application that visualizes NAEP mathematics and reading results from 1990 to 2019. Delegated tasks and code reviews.
- Collaborated with designers to automate the production of over 10 unique reports featuring custom-designed LaTeX templates embedded with ggplot2 visualizations.
- Wrote R scripts to review data sets in longitudinal surveys to meet compliance standards.

FREELANCE/INDEPENDENT CONTRACTOR

The Ballengee Group (November 2014 - February 2015)

• Web-scraped baseball-reference.com to create a database of minor league baseball statistics to model salary expectations for over 80 major and minor league baseball players.

SPECIAL EDUCATION TEACHER

Milwaukee Public Schools (Aug 2011 - June 2013)

• Led instruction, developed lesson plans, and created Individualized Education Programs appropriate for students with diverse learning needs and disabilities.

EDUCATION

MASTERS OF ARTS, URBAN EDUCATION

2013

Cardinal Stritch University, Milwaukee, WI

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE, PSYCHOLOGY

2011

University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI

SPECIALTIES

Data Analysis & Processing
Data Visualization
Web Development
Web Scraping
R Package Development
Technical Writing
Workshop Moderation

SKILLS

Data Toolbox

R // D3.js // SQL // Shiny // Excel // LaTeX

Web Development

Javascript // React // React Native // HTML5 // CSS

Teaching

Interactive Workshops //
Lesson Planning //
Differentiated
Instruction //
Accessibility